<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A methodicall preface prefixed before the Epistle of S. Paule to the Romanes very necessary and profitable for the better vnderstandyng of it / made by the right reuerend father and faythfull seruant of Christ Iesus, Martin Luther ; nowe newly translated out of Latin into English, by W.W. ...</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06512</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1353</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22137371</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22137371</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25142</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06512)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25142)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1731:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A methodicall preface prefixed before the Epistle of S. Paule to the Romanes very necessary and profitable for the better vnderstandyng of it / made by the right reuerend father and faythfull seruant of Christ Iesus, Martin Luther ; nowe newly translated out of Latin into English, by W.W. ...</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
                  <author>W. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[53] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Thomas Woodcocke, dwellyng in Paules Churchyard, at the signe of the Blacke Beare,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1594?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of imprint suggested by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Added imprint at colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁸ D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:1"/>
            <p>¶ A Methodicall Preface <hi>prefixed before the Epiſtle</hi> of S. Paule to the Romanes, very neceſſary and profitable <hi>for the better vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by the right reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and faythfull ſeruaunt of Chriſt</hi> Ieſus, <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> nowe <hi>newly tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſh, by W.W. ſtudent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Can there any good thyng come out of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zareth? Come, and ſee.</hi>
               <bibl>Iohn. 1.46.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, for Thomas <hi>Woodcocke, dwellyng in Paules Churchyard, at the Signe of the blacke Beare.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:2"/>
            <head>To the Engliſh Chriſtian Reader, W. W. wiſheth grace, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and peace, with a true and liuely <hi>knowledge of our onely Lorde and omniſufficient Saueour and Redeemer Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doo offer and preſent vnto thee (gentle Reader) here pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Print, this litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,
<note place="margin">Ariſtotle ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that a good thyng, the more comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> it is made, the better it is.</note> first written by that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and godly learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Chriſtes Schoole, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Luther,</hi> in the Germane or Duche tongue, for his owne Countreymen: afterwards tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into Latine, by a learned man, named <hi>Iuſtus Ionas,</hi> that it might be common to moe then it was before: now alſo though plainly, yet faithfully turned into Engliſhe, for the benefite and commoditie of this our Iſraell, by one most ſtudiouſly carefull,
<note place="margin">The vſe of this Preface.</note> and zelouſly deſirous of thy profite. This excellent Preface wyll leade thee as a Lanterne of light to the better vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of that moſt precious, most fruitfull and profitable Epistle of S. Paul to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> which when thou canst well and wiſely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:3"/>first it wyll make thee ready armed, well furniſhed and instructed to withſtand and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare all the popiſh Romanistes (Cods grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt aduerſaries, and enemies to his Gospell) who ſtoutly mainteyne and defend that mans woorkes doo merite and deſerue ſaluation, and ſo preſent vs iust and righteous before God: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it wyll teache thee a Chriſtian life and conuerſation: namely howe thou oughtest to bring foorth the woorthy fruites of Fayth, which alone doth iuſtifie vs before God, becauſe it is (as it were) the hand wherby we apprehend and take hold faſt of the merits of Chriſtes bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Paſſion to be ours. Other branches of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and manners there be in that notable E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle good ſtore. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and peruſe this prologue, and then it willighten thine vnderſtanding ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much in this weighty matter of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this chiefe and principal poynt of Christian religion:
<note place="margin">This high my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie of our ſaluation dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ed of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the Papiſtes.</note> to wyt, whether we be iustified by the workes of the Law, or by the mercy of God only, for the mediation of his ſonne, who was made a ſlaine ſacrifice vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe for vs moſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and miſerable ſinners. After that thou doest fully and perfitly attaine to the true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of it, I doubt not but thou wilt (by the helpe
<pb facs="tcp:25142:3"/>of Gods holy ſpirite woorking mightily in thee) perſeuere and continue faithful vnto the ende, in this doctrine of faith taught here by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle. Only be ſtrong in the Lord,
<note place="margin">1. Timoth. 1.19</note> fight a good fight, keeping faith and a good conſcience: then ſurely this godly doctrine wyll prepare thy hart in a ſtrong defence, that the fierie dartes of the Dyuels Ministers by errours and falſhood ſhal not wounde thee. Wherfore (gentle Reader) vſe this Introduction to thy comfort and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie: Reade and regard it, and geue God the glorye, who be prayſed for euer and euer. Amen. Farewel in the Lord, and pray for me, as I dayly doo for thee.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>EPHES. 2. VERS. 8. &amp;. 9.</bibl>
               <p>¶ By grace are yee ſaued through fayth, and that not of your ſelues. For it is the gyfte of God, and commeth not of woorkes: leaſt any man ſhoulde boaſt hym ſelfe.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:4"/>
            <head>A Methodicall Preface prefixed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Epiſtle of S. Paul to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, <hi>written by Martin Luther: and Engliſhed by W. W.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing that this Epiſtle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the <hi>Romans</hi> is the Methode of the whole Scripture, and the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Epitome or Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is, of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell (which verily alone it doth briefly &amp; moſt purely ſet out vnto vs) I account it woorthy not only of all Chriſtians to be knowen from their childhood, yea and learned without the booke,
<note place="margin">The excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of this Epiſtle.</note> word by word: but alſo (being by day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and continual meditation as it were chew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and concocted) euen as wel digeſted meat to deſcend and enter into our innermoſt bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. This Epiſtle is ſuch a riche treaſurie of ſpirituall wealth, and as it were a moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull <hi>Copiae Cornu,</hi> that he that readeth it a thouſand tymes, ſhall alwayes meete with ſome new thing not perceyued before. In ſo much that the reading of this Epiſtle is moſt profitable of all other, becauſe it dooth (as it were) aſcende higher in the doctrine of holy things, in the knowledge of Chriſt, in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:25142:4"/>the nature of fayth, &amp; in the knowledge of all ſpirituall affections: yea, the more it is handled, the greater it groweth, more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and delightful, more precious and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous it ſhoweth and ſeemeth then before. Wherfore I thought it labour wel beſtowed, if (accordyng to that meaſure of grace which I haue receyued of God) I might put to my helping hand, and by this briefe Preface pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare an enery into it: to the end that it might more eaſily and playnly be read &amp; vnderſtood of all. Chiefely knowing that this Epiſtle (which one alone ought to be accounted the <hi>Index</hi> and Methode of all the Scriptures) hath ben ſo obſcured and darkened by certayn mens fooliſh Commentaries, Gloſes, and vayne ſubtilties, that very fewe Writers in many ages paſt haue perceyued the drift, ſcope, meaning, and intention of the Apoſtle, which notwithſtanding of it ſelfe is moſt eaſy and playne.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all we muſt diligently ſearch out and labour to knowe the nature of woordes, and figuratiue ſpeaches which the Apoſtle v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. And before all thyngs we muſt learne to know what <hi>S. Paule</hi> meaneth by theſe and ſuch lyke woords: <hi>The Lawe, Sinne, Grace,
<note place="margin">Marke theſe woordes.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25142:5"/>Fayth, Righteouſneſſe, Fleſhe, Spirit. &amp;c.</hi> Otherwiſe though thou reade diligently, thou looſeſt all thy labour.</p>
            <p>This word <hi>Lawe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>awe what it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and how it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erſtoode.</note> muſt not here be taken after the vſual maner of the Philoſophers, or accordyng to common reaſon: namely, to be defined a Doctrine which teacheth men what to doo, and what to leaue vndone. For humane or mans lawes are ſatiſfyed, if a man doo the externall and outwarde worke onely, though in his hart he doo it vnwillyngly. But God, ſeeing he knoweth the hart, iudgeth accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſecret and internall motions of the hart. Therfore the Law of God requireth the hart &amp; affections, or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions therof, neyther is it ſatiſfyed by the externall deede dooyng, vnles they be done with a chearfull hart wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and with all thy affection. Inſomuch as it dooth reproue and rebuke nothing ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly,
<note place="margin">Phariſaicall woorkes.</note> as thoſe glorious and fained works, that is, Hypocriſie, Lying, and the deceyt of the hart.</p>
            <p>Hereupon it is that the Prophete ſayth in the .115. Pſalme, <hi>All men are lyers.</hi> Wherfore by nature they cannot fulfyll the Law. For all men naturally are bent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to euyll, and therfore hate the Lawe.
<pb facs="tcp:25142:5"/>Now wherſoeuer there is not a cheareful and ready wyl to God and his lawe, there is ſinne and the wrath of God, though by ſuch hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie thou doeſt the externall woorke.</p>
            <p>Vppon theſe <hi>Paul</hi> inferreth in his ſecond Chapter, that all the Iewes (although in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall workes they make ſemblance to fulfyl the Law) are ſinners and tranſgreſſors of the Law. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>not the hearers of the law, but the doers therof ſhal be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted iuſt before God.</hi> Wherby he doth intimate vnto vs, that no man can fulfyll the Law by doing the outward worke. Thou ſayſt,
<note place="margin">Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to the Iewes.</note> that a man ſhould not commit adultry, and yet thou thy ſelfe committeſt adultry. In this that thou iudgeſt another, thou condemneſt thyne owne ſelf. For thou that iudgeſt, doeſt the very ſame thyngs. As if he ſhould ſay, Thou in deede after a glorious kynd of hypocriſie, walkeſt in the external works of the Law, and thou iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt others which walke not ſo. In deede thou teacheſt other men, and thou ſeeſt a mote in thy neighbours eye: but thou ſeeſt not the beame which is in thine own eye. For though thou ſeeme to fulfyll the Law in thy externall actions, eyther for feare of puniſhment, or for loue of thy ſelf: yet notwithſtanding thou doſt
<pb facs="tcp:25142:6"/>all theſe thyngs with an vnwillyng mynd, with an hard ſtubborne hart, without al loue and good affection toward God and his law. Inſomuch that thou haddeſt rather there wer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neyther Law nor law geuer at all: that ſo thy luſt and concupiſcence might not be repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is manifeſt, that though in outwarde woorke thou dooeſt counterfeyt the Law, yet in very deede thou dooſt hate and abhorre it. So the Apoſtle ſpeaketh: What is thy righteouſnes woorth (ſaith he) if thou teachyng other men not to ſteale, yet in thy hart thou art inclined toſtealyng: which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection out of all doubt would breake out into the deede doyng, but that thou art afrayde of puniſhment to enſue. For the externall woorke for the moſt part wyll breake out at length, though it be for a tyme diſſembled: this oftentymes foloweth in ſuch hypocrites. Wherfore (as he ſayth) thou which teacheſt another, teacheſt not thy ſelfe, that is, thou art ignorant thy ſelfe what thou teacheſt, becauſe thou art ignorant of the meanyng of the law, how that it is not ſatiſfyed but with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward affection and motion of thyne hart. The Law beyng done in the outward worke only,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:6"/>is ſo farre from iuſtifying,
<note place="margin">The Law on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth ſyn.</note> that it rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth and augmenteth our ſinne, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith in the .v. chapter of this Epiſtle. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, the better thou vnderſtandeſt the Law, the leſſe thou loueſt the law: becauſe it dooth exact &amp; require of thee ſo many thyngs quite contrary to thy affections, and altogether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to thy nature. Hereupon it is that in the .vii. chap. he ſaith: The law is ſpirituall: as if he ſhould ſay, If the law were carnall or moral doctrine only, then it would be ſatiſfied by the external worke. But ſeeing that now it is ſpirituall, that is, requiryng the affect and ſpirit: it foloweth, that no man can fulfyll it, vnles he doth thoſe things which the law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, with a chearefull hart, with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ardent feruencie of mynd, and with all his affection. Such a new hart, and ſuch a feruent and chearefull affection of the harte thou canſt not obtaine of thyne own ſtrength, or by thyne owne merites: but onely by the operation and ſecrete inſtinct of the holye Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>For it is the ſpirit of God only that gyues a new hart, &amp; that makes a man ſpirituall: that ſo he beyng made ſpirituall, he may loue the Law which is ſpirituall, and may fulfyll it,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:7"/>not for feare, or loue of commoditie, but with a chearefull and wyllyng hart, and that he may be caryed violently (as it were with a certayne force) to doo thoſe thyngs which the Law commaundeth, freely, and of his owne accord. So is that ſaying to be vnderſtood. The Law is ſpiritual, that is, the Law is not fulfylled but by the ſpirit, but by a hart renued by the Spirit. Therfore where there is not that renouation of the hart by the ſpirit, there remayneth that greeuous hatred of the lawe, (which law neuertheleſſe of it ſelfe is iuſt, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and good) ſo farre is it from fulfilling it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore accuſtome and acquaynt thy ſelfe with this Phraſe and manner of ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king which the Apoſtle here vſeth. It is one thing to doo the worke of the lawe, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to fulfill the law. For it is a worke of the law when without grace,
<note n="1" place="margin">workes of the Lawe.</note> without the Spirit we begin to worke well, and when we labour to fulfill the lawe by our owne proper ſtrength and power of our free will. But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that there alwayes remayneth in the hart certayne ſeruile feare and a moſt deadly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of the law, ſure it is that ſuch workes are ſinne &amp; haynous factes agaynſt the lawe and ſo doo not pleaſe God. So the Apoſtle ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:25142:7"/>in the .iii. Chapter: By the workes of the law ſhall no fleſh be iuſtified in his ſight. Here therefore we may knowe and acknowledge how the Sophiſters and ſchoole doctors are farre wyde from the the truth, who teach and affirme this wicked and blaſphemous aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: that by our workes we may prepare the way vnto grace. But how can I prepare for my ſelfe a way to grace by that worke which I doo with a ſtubborne, frowarde, and vnto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward harte, and with a repugnant affection: How can that worke be acceptable to God which I doo not willyngly but with great greefe of harre, yea with extreme hatred of the lawe:</p>
            <p>To fulfill the lawe,
<note n="2" place="margin">Fulfyllyng of the Lawe.</note> is to doo thoſe things which the lawe commaundeth with a cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and willing harte, that is, freely and of thyne owne accorde to lyue vnto God, and to worke well, though there were no law at all.</p>
            <p>Such a cherefulnes, readines, willingnes and ardent affection cannot come into our hartes but by the quickening ſpirit and his lyuely impulſions and agitations in our hart, as the Apoſtle ſayth in the .v. Chapter.
<note place="margin">Chap. 1. verſ. 16.</note> Now the Spirit is geuen only by fayth in Ieſus Chriſt, as the Apoſtle ſayd in the beginning.
<pb facs="tcp:25142:8"/>Fayth commeth through the hearing of the Goſpel, through which worde Chriſt is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vnto vs, to haue dyed, to haue bene bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to haue riſen agayne from death for vs, as he ſayth in the .iii. iiii. and .x. Chapters. Therefore our whole iuſtification is of God: Fayth alſo and the Spirit are of God: they come not of our ſelues. Wherefore let vs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that Fayth alone iuſtifyeth and that Fayth alone fulfilleth the lawe. For Fayth through the merit of Chriſt obtayneth the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit, which ſpirit dooth make vs newe hartes, dooth exhilarate vs, dooth excyte and inflame our hart that it may doo thoſe things willingly of loue which the Lawe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and ſo at the laſt good workes in deede doo proceede freely from the fayth whiche worketh ſo myghtily, and which is ſo liuely in our harts. This is the meaning of the thirde Chapter. For whereas he had vtterly dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the workes of the lawe, and myght haue ſeemed to haue diſanulled and aboliſhed the lawe by teaching the doctrine of faith, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth that obiection in theſe wordes. We doo not (ſayth he) deſtroy the Lawe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eſtabliſh it. That is, we teach how the lawe may truely be fulfilled by fayth .i. by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing
<pb facs="tcp:25142:8"/>in Chriſt Ieſu.</p>
            <p>Now it remayneth that we ſhewe howe this word <hi>(Sinne)</hi> is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Scriptures.
<note n="2" place="margin">Sinne what it is.</note> 
               <hi>Sinne</hi> in the Sriptures ſignifieth not onely the externall worke: but that whole force and natiue operation incredulitie, as that wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which we haue by lineall deſcent (as it were) from our great Graundfather olde A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, which euen violently carryeth vs head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to ſinne, namely that wicked hart and al our reaſon, with al (yea euen his beſt and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt) his ſtrength and power wherewith we can doo nothing els but ſinne: ſo that then we are ſaid to commit ſinne, when by the efficacy of this originall ſinne (as with a certayne vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent force) we are caryed headlong to doo euill. There is no outwarde ſinne doone but firſt by this naturall force and impulſion a man is wholly and with all his affection cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed roundly awaye to ſinnyng. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and God hym ſelfe, when they ſpeake of ſinne, they haue reſpect vnto this wickednes of our hartes, vnto this naturall inclination, that is, this vice of incredulitie, as to the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne of all other ſinnes. Lyke as therefore Fayth alone dooth iuſtifye, and alone dooth obtayne the Spirit and power to fulfill the
<pb facs="tcp:25142:9"/>Law, and to doo thoſe works in deede which are onely good: ſo onely incredulitie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe cauſeth ſinne, and exciteth and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the fleſh to ſin, and to commit euil works, as we ſee it happened to Adam and Eue in Paradiſe. <hi>Geneſis. 3.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore Chriſt alſo in the Goſpell cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth only &amp; cheefly incredulitie,
<note place="margin">Sinne is prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe.</note> ſinne. <hi>Iohn. 16</hi> The Spirit (ſayth he) ſhall reproue the world of ſinne, bicauſe they haue not beleeued in me. Thoſe woorkes which be truely good, euen as good fruites cannot proceede and ſpring but of a good tree, that is, of fayth working in the hart: as contrarywiſe euill fruit can not come but from an euill tree, that is, increduli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the hart.</p>
            <p>Therfore this wickednes and incredulitie in the harte is euery where in the Scriptures called the heade of the Serpent and of the old Dragon,
<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> whiche was to be broken by that bleſſed ſeede of the woman, namely Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But nowe to proceede:
<note n="3" place="margin">Grace what it is.</note> As concerning theſe two words <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Gyft,</hi> they differ thus. <hi>Grace</hi> is the fauour, mercy, and free good will and beneuolence of God towardes vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gyft</hi> is the holy ſpirit hym ſelfe whom
<note n="4" place="margin">Gyft what it is.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:25142:9"/>God dooth ſend into theyr hartes whom he hath taken mercy vpon, and whom he fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: as very well appeareth in the .v. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: where he diſtinguiſheth gyft from grace. Although now we haue not the fulnes of this gyft or of the Spirit (bicauſe in this life there will alwayes remayne in vs remnaunites of ſinne which fight agaynſt the Spirit, as the Apoſtle ſayth in the .vii. Chapter and the .iii. to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> as alſo Moſes ſayth in the iii. of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> that there will be a conflict be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſeede of the woman and the ſeede of the Serpent) yet grace worketh this in vs, that the reliques of ſinne ſhall not be imputed vnto vs: but that we ſhall be reputed and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted before God as men fully and perfitly iuſt. Neyther is the grace and fauour of God ſo imperfectly beſtowed vpon vs, as we ſayd the gyft was. For God rather dooth loue ande imbrace vs with a full fauour and a right perfect good will for Chriſtes ſake, who is our mediator, earneſt penney, and the firſt finites of the Spirit. Therefore though rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts of ſinne doo dayly gliſter and ſhine in vs: yet neuer theles we are iuſt before God, and ſyil is not imputed vnto vs through faith which daly ſtriueth and wageth war againſt
<pb facs="tcp:25142:10"/>the fleſhe.</p>
            <p>So then you may vnderſtand that place in the .vii. Chapter: where the Apoſtle, though he was iuſtified in the Spirite, acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth hymſelfe yet to be a ſinner: and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he ſayth in the .viii. Chapter: there is now no condemnation to thoſe which are in Chriſt Ieſu. As many therefore of vs as are through faith iuſtified in Chriſt, we are both ſinners and iuſt. Sinners by reaſon of the imperfect mortification of our fleſhe, and for that in this lyfe (the reliques of ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayning in vs) we cannot haue or attayne the fulnes of the Spirit. Firſt bycauſe wee haue through fayth the firſt fruites and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of the ſpirit: ſo that for our faith in Chriſt, God fatherly fauoring vs, dooth not impute vnto vs that ſinne whiche remayneth in our fleſh: neyther dooth iudge vs vntill that ſinne by death be quite broken, baniſhed, and aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <p>But now let vs ſpeake ſomewhat of fayth.
<note n="5" place="margin">Fayth what it is.</note> Fayth is not a certain cold opinion or a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring cogitation of a mans mynde, ſuche a one as any man (hearing the hiſtorye of the Goſpell) may fooliſhly imagin hym ſelfe to haue.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:10"/>
            <p>For certayne men (hearing many things preached of fayth, and ſeeing that they can diſpute many things of fayth and of Chriſt, and yet for all that by that knowledge, cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or diligent meditation, perceyue them ſelues not to be foorthwith incited to do good workes) fall into that wicked and impious error, that they ſtoutly deny man to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by fayth alone: but that alſo woorkes are required. Theſe men in deede hearing the Goſpel, fayne vnto themſelues a certayne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and they reuolue in their myndes cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne colde cogitations of Chriſt, thinking then that fayth is nothing but the dreame of their owne mynde and thoſe vayne cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<note place="margin">A fayned fayth.</note> And theſe men now and then boult out theſe excellent ſpeaches. O (ſay they) if faith only iuſtifieth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I pray you what ſay you to this: Behold I haue heard the Goſpel prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: I remember the hiſtory of Chriſt: Lo, I beleeue, and yet I am not iuſtifyed. True <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t is, for bycauſe this thy Fayth is nothing but thyne owne bare and naked imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and cogitation of fayth which dooth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ot innouate thy hart, and which doth moue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee nothing at all, there followeth no newnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f lyfe, no workes of fayth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:11"/>
            <p>But a true fayth is the worke of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are regenerate and borne anew by his Spirit. <hi>Iohn. 1.</hi> Chapter: wherby alſo our old Adam is quelled, and we being wholy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, we are made (as the Apoſtle ſayth) newe creatures to Chriſt, the holy Ghoſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lyfe and gonernment of our hartes.
<note place="margin">Fayth is liuely and not idle.</note> Wherefore fayth is ſuch an effectuall, lyuely, quicke, and myghty operation in our harte, that it cannot be idle, but muſt needes breake out and ſhew it ſelfe by good workes.</p>
            <p>Neyther dooth he that hath this Fayth care greatly whether good workes be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded or no. For though there were no lawe at all, yet by this lyuely impulſion working in his hart he is of his owne accorde forced and caryed to worke true and godly Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> workes.</p>
            <p>He that dooth not his good workes of ſuch a lyuely affection of the hart, is wholy in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe, and a ſtraunger and aliant from the fayth, as many of thoſe be which in ſchooles diſpute and iangle much of Fayth and good workes, not knowing what they ſpeake, or what they holde and affirme.
<note place="margin">A true defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of faith.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fayth therefore is a conſtant truſt and a
<pb facs="tcp:25142:11"/>ſure confidence of the mercy of God towards vs, which is liuely, and worketh myghtely in our harts, whereby we committe our ſelues wholy to God, caſting all our care vpon hym: leaning and truſting aſſuredly to this fayth, we are not afrayde to dye a thouſand tymes. For this ſo bolde an aſſurance of the mercy and fauour of God dooth make our hartes merry, glad, and lyght: doth alſo erect, rayſe, and euen rauiſh vs with moſt ſweete motions and affections towardes God: yea and dooth ſo embolden the harte of the true beleeuer, that truſting to haue God on his ſide, he is not afrayde to oppoſe hymſelfe alone agayuſt all creatures. But it is the Spirite of God which geueth vs this heroicall harte and ſtout ſtomacke through fayth, which working ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually in our hartes, dooth incyte and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame vs to doo good. Now we haue thys chearefull towardnes and forwardnes, to the ende that wee myght be moſte prompt and ready willingly and of our owne accorde to doo, tolerate, and ſuffer all things, whereby we may be obedient to ſo gentle and fauora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a father, who through Chriſte hath inry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched vs with ſo great abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of his graces. It can not poſſibly be but that in whom ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:25142:12"/>this efficacy and lyfe of fayth is, it ſhould dayly worke,
<note place="margin">A liuely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.</note> fructifye, and geue increaſe to God. Euen as it is vnpoſſible that a fyre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindled &amp; flaming, ſhould not geue lyght and caſt foorth brightnes, wherefore watch thou and take heede that thou doo not beleeue eyther thyne owne vayne ſonges and ſoimdes of fayth,
<note place="margin">Fancyes.</note> thyne owne fonliſh imaginations, or the vayne trifling ſtuffe of Sophiſters.
<note place="margin">Blynd pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes.</note> For theſe Sophiſters haue neyther wyt nor wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. They are belly beaſtes borne onely to thoſe feaſtes of ſchooles. But pray thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God (who commaundeth by his worde that lyght ſhould ſhine out of darkenes) that hee would ſhyne bryghtly in thyne hart, and that be would create a true Fayth in thee: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe thou ſhalt neuer beleeue truely though for the ſpace of a thouſand yeares thou diddeſt labour and ſtudy about ſuch cogitations and imaginations, either of a faith heretofore got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<note place="margin">Righteouſnes.</note> or hereafter to be ſought for. This fayth now is, that true iuſtice whiche the Apoſtle calleth the iuſtice and righteouſnes of God, that is, which onely is of force auaylable and can ſtand before God: bycauſe it is the mere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyft of God. And this fayth dooth tranſforme the whole man and makes hym ſuch an one,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:12"/>that (according to that common definition of ciuill iuſtice) he is ready to geue and render to euery one that which is due vnto hym. For ſeeing by that fayth we are inſtified and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the loue of the lawe of God, then ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we (ſo magnifying God and the lawe) doo geue that glory vnto God which is due vnto hym. Alſo ſeeing by that fayth we doo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue firmely that we are iuſtified freely, and reconciled vnto God through Chriſt, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where is ready to ſaue vs, then by courſe we ſerue for our neighbor, &amp; ſo agayne render and attribute to euery man that which is his. This ryghteouſnes of the hart we can not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne by any indeuour of our own free will, or by our own ſtrength &amp; merits. For as no man can ſee that lyuely operation, that is, fayth of our harts, but onely God: ſo no man can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell from hymſelfe that wickednes and incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie of the hart but onely by grace and the Spirit of God: ſo farre we are from being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to deliuer our ſelues from ſinnes by our owne power. Therefore though workes doo ſeeme to ſhow gallantly and gloriouſly: yet notwithſtanding whatſoeuer is not of fayth, is hipocriſie and ſinne.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning fleſh and ſpirit which
<pb facs="tcp:25142:13"/>often are vſed in this Epiſtle: you muſt not take fleſh to be (after the common manner) the deſires and luſtes of the fleſh onely, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt you cal the ſpirit onely thoſe things whiche are doone ſpiritually in the inwarde corners of the hart.
<note n="6" place="margin">fleshe what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is.</note> For the Apoſtle Saynt Paule (as alſo Chriſt hymſelfe in the .iii. Ch. of <hi>Iohn</hi>) doo call fleſh, whatſoeuer is borne of the fleſhe, that is, the whole man bodye and ſoule, al mans reaſon wholy with all his chee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and beſt powers: Bycauſe that all theſe things doo ſauour of nothing but fleſhe, and ſeeke after nothing but fleſhly things. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou ſhalt eall all thoſe workes fleſh, which ſeeme to be good, and make a beautiful ſhow of holy workes, and yet are doone with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the grace and working of the holy Spirit of God in the hart. Which thing is playne and euident by the .v. Chapter to the <hi>Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> where Paule reckeneth and counteth he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies &amp; ſects amongſt the fruites of the fleſh. And in the .viii. Chapter to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> he ſayth, that the law is made weake, by reaſon of the fleſh, which thing ought to be ment not onely of the vnchaſte luſtes of the fleſh, but alſo of the whole maſſe of corruption and wickednes: yea breiſly and cheifly of incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie
<pb facs="tcp:25142:13"/>or vnbeleefe,
<note place="margin">Incredulitie the ground all ſines.</note> which is the moſt ſecret and cheife ſinne of all.</p>
            <p>Contrarywiſe,
<note n="7" place="margin">Spirite what it is.</note> thou ſhalt call the Spirit thoſe ſpirituall things, euen thoſe externall works which proceede from a ſpiritual man, or from a hart innouated and made newe by the holy ſpirit. That waſhing of the feete which Chriſt did to his Diſciples, though it was an outward worke, yet it was ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>Peters fiſhing, to which he returned being now iuſtified in the ſpirit, was alſo ſpirituall. Therefore that is fleſhe, whatſoeuer a man dooth, ſeeking and ſauoring onely carnal and fleſhly things. And that is Spirit, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is doone within or without, wherewith a man exerciſing fayth and Charitie, dooth ſeeke ſpirituall things. Vnles we take theſe wordes in this ſenſe, we ſhall neyther vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this Epiſtle of S. Paul, nor any other bookes of the diuine Scriptures. Therefore whether it be <hi>Ierome,</hi> or <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> or <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> or <hi>Origen:</hi> breifly what writers ſoeuer they be that vſe theſe wordes otherwiſe, let not the authoritie of men moue thee any thing at al, but rather flee from them al as from the plague and peſtilence. But now ſet vs come
<pb facs="tcp:25142:14"/>to handle the Epiſtle it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore it is the duetie and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of an Euangeliſt or preacher of glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> godly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>uction for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaders.</note> firſt of all to preach the Lawe and to ſhewe how that all men (which are without the circuite and compaſſe of grace and fayth in Chriſt) are the ſons and children of wrath, are ſinners, and can do nothing but ſinne, that ſo they acknowledging theyr miſerye and wretchednes with an humble and contrite hart, myght thirſt after grace, the Apoſtle S. Paule in this firſt Chapter dooth firſt of all finde fault with the vnbeleefe,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap: </seg>1</label> and checketh and rebuketh thoſe groſſe ſinnes which aptly and playnly were knowen to be manifeſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,
<note place="margin">The maner of S. Paules do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</note> as were the Idolatry and ſuch groſſe ſinnes of the Gentiles: as alſo are of thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which at this day being ignorant of God, voyde of grace, and without the Spirit, doo lyue in blyndnes and darkenes. The wrath of God is reuealed by the Goſpell (ſayth the Apoſtle) from heauen agaynſt all vngodlines and vnrighteouſnes of men which withholde the truth in vnrighteouſnes. For though man myght knowe by the Creatures that there was a God: yet notwithſtanding his nature is euil and wicked, inſomuch that it dooth not
<pb facs="tcp:25142:14"/>glorify hym, nor geue hym thankes, but being blynded dooth alwayes geue ouer it ſelfe to worſe and worſe, vntill they doo not only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit idolatry and all kynde of wickednes, but alſo fauour them that do them, and geue their conſent and agreement to thoſe which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch things.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond Chap. he doth more at large ſhew that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe little holy ones,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>2</label>
               <note place="margin">The Iewes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yll or woorſe ſinners than the Gentiles.</note> and thoſe glorious hypocrites (as namely the Iewes then, and now in theſe dayes all the Iuſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes which go about by their owne ſtrength and power to fulfill the lawe) are alſo ſinners, who dooing outwardly the good workes of the lawe: notwithſtanding inwardly nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing that greife of their hart, doo hate the lawe.</p>
            <p>And theſe (as ryght hypocrites commonly vſe to doo) are very quicke to condemne and iudge other men, counting themſelues holy and pure when as they are full of malice and enuy, fraude, deceyte, and all kynde of fylthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vncleannes, as Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Math. 23.</hi> And theſe are they which fayning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues holy, contemne and deſpiſe in very deed the great goodnes of God, and accordyng to the hardnes of theyr hartes, heape and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:25142:15"/>vp vnto them ſelues wrath, agaynſt the day of wrath. <hi>Paul</hi> therfore as a true Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt fyrſt of all preacheth the Law,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſinners</note> conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludyng all men alyke to be ſynners, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncyng to all the wrath of God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they whiche marke well, by the power of theyr owne nature or free wyll, are ſo farre from beyng any better than thoſe groſſe and open ſinners mentioned in the fyrſt Chapter: that the Apoſtle calleth them obſtinate, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne, men that cannot repent, aliantes, and ſtraungers.</p>
            <p>In the thirde Chapter he declareth that both the Iewes &amp; the Gentiles are alyke ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners before God:
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>3</label>
               <note place="margin">Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Iewe and Gentile.</note> notwithſtanding that the Iewes are preferred and excell the Gentiles in this prerogatiue, namely, for that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God did belong to them, and alſo for that the words and Oracles of God were committed vnto them. And thoughe ſome of the Iewes did not beleue, yet for all that their vnbeliefe made not the faithful truth of Gods promiſe vayne, voyde, or without effect: and to proue this, he allegeth that place of the. 51. Pſalme: as it is written (ſayeth he) That thou mighteſt be iuſtified in thy woords, and ouercome when thou art iudged. After thys
<pb facs="tcp:25142:15"/>he returneth agayn to his cauſe and purpoſe, and proueth by the Scriptures, that al are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually ſinners without any exception, and that no man is iuſtified by the woorkes of the lawe: but that onely by the lawe commeth the knoweledge of ſinne. Finally he teacheth the true and right waye of righteouſnes and ſaluation. All (ſayeth he) haue ſinned,
<note place="margin">The hye way to righteouſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, is by fait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Chriſt.</note> and are deſtitute and depriued of the glory of God: but they are iuſtified freely by his grace, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus whom God hath ſet forth to be a reconciliatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through fayth in his blood. And a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: But now (ſayth he) is the righteouſnes of God made manifeſt without the law, being approued by the Teſtimony &amp; witnes of the lawe and the Prophets, to witte, the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of God, by the faith of Ieſu Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all &amp; vppon all that beleeue. So then the lawe is eſtabliſhed through fayth, althoughe woorks and glorying in the works of the law are excluded by fayth.</p>
            <p>Seeing therfore in the three former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, he hath taught, that all men are ſinners: &amp; alſo hath ſhewed that onely fayth in Chriſt, is the waye vnto righteouſnes, and meanes to iuſtification,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>4</label> by &amp; by in this fourth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:25142:16"/>he anſweareth to certayne obiections and cauils. As for the moſt part, when Chriſt or fayth is taught (that is, that our woorkes are nothing, that we are onely iuſtified by fayth) ſtreight wayes certayne Iuſticiaries obiect: If fayth alone dooth iuſtifie, then we muſt ceaſe altogether to do good works, then good woorks are to be omitted and left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. The Apoſtle anſweareth, propoſing the example of Abraham: <hi>What ſhall wee ſay then, that Abraham our Father hath found concerning the fleſhe? Did he me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite nothing at all by hys woorks?</hi> He concludeth, that Abraham was iuſtified onely by fayth without any woorks, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the Scripture ſayth, that Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham (before hee was circumciſed) beleeued God, and it was counted and reputed vnto hym for righteouſnes. <hi>Geneſis. 15.6.</hi> If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the woorke of circumciſion which God commaunded (which was a precious woorke of obedience) profited Abraham nothing to iuſtificaton, then it is moſt ſure and certaine, that there is none other worke which is auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable to iuſtification. But as circumciſion being an outward ſigne,
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> apt ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>de.</note> was vnto Abraham a ſeale of his righteouſnes by faith: ſo good
<pb facs="tcp:25142:16"/>woorks are onely an externall ſigne, whiche doth not iuſtifie, but which doth ſignifie vnto men, that a man is inwardly iuſtified before God, and they doo teſtifie and approue as certayne ſignes and fruites, that liuely faith, which worketh in the hart. By this, as by the moſt graue, weighty, and authentike ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the Apoſtle doth confirme, and build out of the Scriptures his doctrine of fayth delyuered out, and taught in the third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Furthermore the Apoſtle allegeth the teſtimony of Dauid in his 32. Pſal. to proue this matter. Alſo in moſt playne woords he affirmeth that a man is iuſtified by the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of righteouſnes, without woorkes: althoughe (as I haue ſayd before) woorkes doo followe thoſe that are iuſtified by Faith. Moreouer he dilateth and amplyfieth the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample againſt all other woorks of the lawe, inferring that the Iewes are not therfore ſtreightwaye the true heyres of Abraham, bycauſe their ſtocke and pedigrue is deriued from the circumciſed Abraham, or bycauſe they receyued the lawe, vnleſſe they tread and followe the ſteps of fayth,
<note place="margin">Abrahams chyldren muſt haue Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams fayth</note> and beleeuing in Chriſt, imitate the fayth of Abraham: ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally &amp; chiefly, ſeeing that Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the
<pb facs="tcp:25142:17"/>lawe (whether it were of Moſes or of the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion) was iuſtified onely by fayth, and called the father of many nations, that is, of al beleeuers. Finally he concludeth thus: See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the lawe cannot giue that effectuall working, wherby it may willingly and cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully be ſatiſfied: alſo ſeeing that the grudging and murmuring ſtirred vp by the lawe, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and remayneth in vs, and diſdayneth and taketh it greuouſly that there ſhould be any poſitiue lawe ſet downe for her, I ſaye that this hatred againſt the lawe, and the lawge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God himſelfe ſtill continuing, it cannot de that the woorkes of the lawe ſhould pleaſe God: Nay rather ſeeing they proceede from a hart that abhorreth the law &amp; God, they are nothing els but ſinne, and doo alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and kindle the indignation and wrath of God. Wherfore Fayth onely dooth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the bleſſing and grace promiſed to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham. Now it is not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for hym only, but alſo for vs (as Paule ſaith in the latter end of this Chapter) that fayth might alſo be imputed and reckened to vs for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</p>
            <p>In the fifth Chapter, hee intreateth of woorkes, and of the fruites of faith which be
<pb facs="tcp:25142:17"/>theſe: peace, ioy of conſcience, loue towards God &amp; our neighbour: a profitable, couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; bold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence: and a ſtoute &amp; manfull perſeuerance &amp; pacience in tribulations and afflictions, for ſtreight waye theſe fruites followe, whereſoeuer this true faythe is in the hart. Surely that moſt excellent riches, and abundant wealth of the grace of God of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and exhibited to vs in Chriſte (whom God would haue dye for vs, when we were as yet weaklings, yea enemies to God) if ſo be, by fayth it be knowen and acknowledged of vs in our harts, it cannot but inflame vs, and make vs ſtrong and able to doo moſte willingly, cherefully, and readyly, all thoſe things which we knowe wyll pleaſe this our moſt gentle father. Therfore the chiefe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, drift, and ſcope of this Epiſtle ſtands ſtedfaſt and ſure, namely, that by fayth alone we are iuſtified, wythout woorkes, and yet for all that good woorks are not condemned. For thoſe wookes that in deede, and truely may be called good, and thoſe good fruites doo followe fayth, and whereſoeuer fayth is, it cannot chooſe but woorke: Lyke as the flame can not but geue good lyght. Of theſe that be truely good woorks, the Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries
<pb facs="tcp:25142:18"/>(who haue nothing ſo rife in theyr mouths, as works, works, works) know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at al: They do but only imagine in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, certayne cold woorks, which bycauſe they haue no ſparke of faith in them, are void of all ſpirituall affections: as ioye, peace of the conſcience, and that bolde truſt and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in God, and are rotten fruites of a rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tree. After this the Apoſtle maketh a pleaſaunt digreſſion, ſhewing how ſinne and righteouſnes, alſo how death and life came vpon vs. And there he compareth thoſe two, Adam and Chriſt. Wherefore he reaſoneth thus:
<note place="margin">The Apoſtles argument.</note> It was therfore needefull and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, that Chriſt ſhould be ſent, who ſhoulde make his righteouſnes to be ours, by the newe birth or regeneration in fayth and the ſpirit, euen as the old man Adam by propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation left vs his ſinne, throughe that olde generation, according to the fleſh. Againe, by this argument another propoſition is ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grounded, namely, that no man by hys owne ſtrength and power, is able to deliuer hymſelfe from ſinne, or to iuſtifie himſelfe. For it was not in our choyſe to be borne, or not to be borne of the olde Adam, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſhe, which by other Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:18"/>is euident and cleare inoughe. For if the lawe of God (which ſurely, if any other thing in the world myght haue iuſtified, ought to haue preuayled and auayled for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes) dooth not onely not iuſtifie, but rather encreaſeth and augmenteth ſinne in vs, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that grudging and fretting of our nature, dayly ſtomacking and murmuring at God: yea the more it dooth preſſe vs, the more it ſtyrreth vp ſinne in our nature, which goeth agaynſt all, whatſoeuer is forbidden.
<note place="margin">Nitimur in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite ſemper cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pimuſque ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata.</note> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the more perfitly we knowe the lawe, the more miſery we behold in our ſelues, and we ſee the better howe that we haue more neede of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the Sixth Chapter he handleth that great and chiefe woorke of our fayth, to wit,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>6</label> the warfare and conflict of Chriſtians be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the fleſhe and the ſpirit.
<note place="margin">The warfare of Chriſtians.</note> For the fleſhe ſighteth alwayes agayuſt the ſpirit, and the ſpirit wageth warre agaynſt the fleſhe, to the end that the deſires of the fleſhe, and reliques of ſinne, which remayne in vs after iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, might be quite ſuppreſſed, quelled, and quenched in vs.</p>
            <p>And in this Chapter the Apoſtle teacheth, that we are not ſo iuſtified &amp; freed from ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:19"/>by fayth, that ſinne is quite taken awaye, and altogether aboliſhed in vs:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>liques of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nne.</note> but that the reliques of ſinne as yet remayne in vs. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles, thoſe renmaunts of ſinne are not layde to our charge, by reaſon of fayth, which continually wraſtleth wyth the deſires of the fleſhe. Wherefore as yet, bycauſe wh lyue in the fleſhe, that ſtrife and combate endureth in vs, and they that are already iuſtified, haue inoughe to doo, and haue labour inoughe to turne them vnto: yea all their lyfe tyme they may toyle vntill they ſweat agayne, by ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring to tame their fleſhe, to repreſſe the luſts of it,
<note place="margin">Mortification.</note> and to make it ſubiect vnto the Spirit. And by that mortification of our fleſhe, and newenes of our ſpirtuall lyfe, we expreſſe the Death and the Reſurrection of Chriſt, as alſo that ſigne of mortification in Baptiſme, which dooth ſignifie and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto vs no other thing, but this conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall mortification of the fleſhe, and dayly viuification and quickening of the ſpirit. For Baptiſme, that is, this mortification, dooth woorke in vs ſo long, vntill ſinne being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed and abandoned by the death of our bodyes, we riſe in our bodyes wyth Chriſt, and raygne wyth hym for euermore.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:19"/>
            <p>And this thing (namely, the dayly morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of our fleſhe) we may performe, bycauſe we are not vnder the law: but vnder grace. Nowe what it is,
<note place="margin">VVhat it is, not to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law.</note> not to be vnder the lawe, he himſelfe expoundeth. For not to be vnder the lawe, muſt not to be ſo vnderſtood, as thoughe it were lawfull for vs to doo what we liſt: but not to be vnder the lawe is this, that our harts are ſo made newe by the ſpirit, through fayth, that freely, willingly, and of our owne accorde, we may doo that whiche the lawe requires, though there were no law at all. For grace dooth endue vs wyth the loue of the lawe. Wherfore we being iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, haue no more the lawe agaynſt vs,
<note place="margin">VVhat it is to be vnder the Lawe.</note> but agreeing wyth vs. To be vnder the law, is to woorke wythout grace, and not to be able to fulfill the lawe, where there cannot choſe but be ſinne.</p>
            <p>And this nowe at length is the true liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and freedome from the lawe and ſinne, of whiche the Apoſtle here diſputeth, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ende of this Chapter. As for this li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie it is ſuch, that we may willingly from our harts doo good wythout any exaction of the lawe. Therefore it is a ſpirituall liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which dooth not take away the lawe: but
<pb facs="tcp:25142:20"/>giueth and imparteth a certayne power, and ſpirit to fulfill the lawe: namely, a cherefull mynde, a readye will, and feruent deſire to woorke well, whereby it dooth then ſatiſfie the lawe: iuſomuch that it hath not any thing to exact at his hand, or to charge him wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.
<note place="margin">A fyt and apt ſimilitude.</note> Euen as if thou were endebted to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne creditour of thyne, and didſt owe hym a great Summe of money, thou mighteſt after twod wayes ſatiſfie hym, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge thy debt: Firſt by a free forgeuenes of the debt, and cancelling of thy handwri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Secondarily, by ſuretie of another ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who will geue his fayth and trueth for the, promiſing to ſtand to the payment of all the foreſayd money, and ſo by his woorde and Fayth giuen for the obligation, wherewith thou waſt bound, may be blotted and cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, as voyde, and of none effect. Lykewyſe Chriſt hath delyuered vs from the lawe, as from a creditour. Wherefore that liberty is not carnall, whereby it is lawfull to doo what thou wilt: but is altogether labourſome and paynefull, which willingly doth good works: ſo that it needes not any exaction of the lawe.</p>
            <p>In the Seuenth Chapter,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>7</label> he confirmeth
<pb facs="tcp:25142:20"/>this by a certaine ſimilitude of marriage, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the huſband &amp; the wyfe.
<note place="margin">A ſimilitude to proue the libertie from the Lawe.</note> For euen as the woman, if her huſband be deade, is delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the lawe of the man: not ſo freed that ſhe may not marry but, rather contrary: nowe firſt of all ſhe is freed in deede and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that ſhe may marry another man, which ſhe could not doo before ſhee was delyuered from her former huſband: ſo alſo our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is deade to the lawe, as long as olde Adam lyueth in vs. But when this olde A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam is mortified by the ſctirit, there is then liberty for both parties, lyke as I haue ſayd there was betwixt man and wyfe: But the conſcience is not free, ſo that it cannot at all doo any woorke: but rather ſo that nowe hee beginneth to cleaue vnto another, euen vnto Chriſt, that it ſhould bring foorth fruite vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God.</p>
            <p>After this, he dooth at large explicate the nature of ſinne, and of the lawe: ſheewing the lawe to be the force and power of ſinne. For the olde Adam or nature,
<note place="margin">The nature of ſynne.</note> howe muche more it is preſſed down by the law, which of his own ſtrength he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not fulfill) ſo much the more it dooth fret and fume agaynſt it. And no maruayle, ſeeing it can doo nothing of it
<pb facs="tcp:25142:21"/>ſelfe, but ſinne. Therefore the lawe is vnto it a puniſhment, and death: not that the law is euil: but this is done through the faulte of our owne nature, which taketh it greuouſly, that any good ſhould be exacted of it whiche ſhee cannot fulfill: not vnlike a ſickely and weake man who is heauely diſpleaſed, if any man require of him to doo thoſe woorkes, or that mayne ſtrength which is in a ſound and ſtrong man.</p>
            <p>Wherfore Paul here inferreth,
<note place="margin">The nature of the Lawe.</note> that the law, the more exactly and throughly it is knowen, dooth woorke in vs nothing els, but this, that it dooth the more ſhew our ſinne and increaſe it: by which it dooth ſlaye vs, and make vs guiltie of eternall death, and of the wrath of God. But of this matter no man can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute better then he, whoſe conſcience hath felt &amp; had trial of the terror of the law: whoſe conſcience hath fele that ſhaking and quaking (as it were) the very fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations of the earth, and who hath wel perceyned it at ſome time, or other to haue cauſed a great tumult in hys hart. Therfore we haue neede of a more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and myghtier force in our harts, to iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vs than the law is. Truely they that haue not ſo knowen the lawe, they are altogether
<pb facs="tcp:25142:21"/>blynd, and walke in this lyfe in a certayne bolde confidence, thinking that they can ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyll the lawe by their woorks: not conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at all, howe that the lawe dooth impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly requyre the whole hart, and all the affection. Wherefore theſe men behold not the end of the lawe: onely they vewe the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and hid face of Moſes wythout grace, who are lyke perpetually to periſhe in theyr vayne woorks.</p>
            <p>After theſe matters,
<note place="margin">The ſtrife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the fleſh and the ſpirit, euen in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate.</note> the Apoſtle ſetteth foorth, howe the fleſhe and the Spirit in one and the ſame man dooth ſtryne and wraſtle together: and he exhibiteth hymſelfe vnto vs, as an example (thoughe he was inſtifyed.) Whereby we myght learne this mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the remnaunts of ſinne. Nowe hee calleth both the Spirit and the fleſhe, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne lawe. <hi>I haue found</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>a lawe in my members contrary and repugnant &amp;c.</hi> For lyke as the lawe of God doth vrge and exact thoſe things to be done of vs, which God woulde haue done: ſo the Lawe of the members or of the fleſh, dooth incite and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell vs to carnall things, contrary to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Agayne on the other ſide, the ſpirit doth labour myghtely agaynſt the fleſhe, mouing
<pb facs="tcp:25142:22"/>vs to ſpirituall things. And this conflict &amp; combate dureth ſo long as we are clothed wyth this fleſhe. In this man the ſtryfe is ſtronger and myghtier: in that man more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe and fainte: in euerye man accordingly as the ſpirit or fleſhe is in hym, ſtronger or weaker: notwythſtanding one and the ſame man is that fleſhe and ſpirit, which ſo ſtryueth and wraſtleth wyth himſelfe, vntill (Sinne being quyte aboliſhed) hee become ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
            <p>In the eight Chapter,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>8</label> he comforteth thoſe which fight ſo wyth their owne fleſhe:
<note place="margin">A comfort for the afflicted conſcience of the godly.</note> Alſo he declareth that the reliques of ſinne cannot hurt vs: that there is no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnation to thoſe which are in Ieſus Chriſt, which walke not after the fleſh, but according to the ſpirit. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, he dooth explicate at large the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fleſh and the ſpirit, ſhewing that the ſpirit is geuen to man onely by Chriſt. He that hath not the ſpirie of Chriſt (ſaith he) the ſame man is none of his. Agayne, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as are led by the ſpirit of God, they are the Sonnes of God. For it is the Spirite alone whiche dooth innouate and renewe our hartes, which dooth make them ſpiritual, which dooth incourage vs with ſweete and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:25142:22"/>affects and motions: laſtly which dooth geue teſtimonie and beare witnes vnto our ſpirits, that we are the very ſonnes of God, teaching vs that we (although ſinne dooth boyle with rage within our fleſh) haue God for our father, &amp; may account our ſelues his Sonnes, if ſo be that we doo dayly by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit wraſtle agaynſt the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Now bycauſe nothing is more profitable to the mortifying of the olde Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fleſh, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is, the Apoſtle doth here comfort vs in thoſe tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, affirming that the Spirit dooth make interceſſion and requeſt for vs with ſighes, which cannot be vttered and expreſſed: alſo that all the creatures, being ſubiect to vanity and abuſe, do euen grone and trauel in payne togither with vs, vntill this body of ſinne be aboliſhed, and the glory of the ſonnes of God be reuealed. Thus we ſee that theſe three laſt Chapters, doo vrge nothing ſo much as this onely and chiefe worke of our fayth, namely, the mortification of our olde Adam, which is the fleſh.</p>
            <p>In the .ix. x. and .xi.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chapt. </seg>9. 10. &amp;. 11.</label> Chapters he handleth the matter of Predeſtination. For all the reſt doo depend vpon that: namely, who ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue
<pb facs="tcp:25142:23"/>the worlde, and who ſhoulde not, who ſhould beleeue, and who not, who ſhould be freed from ſinne, who ſhould be blynded, who ſhould be damned, and who ſhould be iuſtified. Seeing therefore that both the ſending out of the preachers of the Goſpell, and the worde it ſelfe be of God, it is certayne that it lyeth onely in Gods hand to iuſtifie vs.
<note place="margin">Predeſtinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be taught and preached.</note> And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this ſtable ſentence and immouable neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of predeſtination, is a moſt neceſſary doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine to be taught. For we are ſo weake that if it were in our handes, very fewe or rather none ſhould be ſaued. For the dyuell would ouercome vs. Yet now ſeeing this ſentence and decree of God is moſt ſure and certayne, ſo that it cannot be chaunged or altered by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny creature, we haue then good hope to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come at the length thoſe reliques of ſinne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that now they rage in our fleſh.</p>
            <p>But here thoſe curious men (who before they haue learned Chriſt,
<note place="margin">A Caneat for curious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</note> and the vertue of his Croſſe, doo ſearch the profunditie and depth of predeſtination, laboring in vaine to inquire whether they are predeſtinate to life or death) muſt be rayned, ſtrayned and kept backe with ſome holy Brydle. For without all doubt, theſe men by this their fooliſh curioſitie, will
<pb facs="tcp:25142:23"/>leade and learne to caſt them ſelues headlong into the confuſion of their conſcience, or into the bottomles pit of deſperation. But thou (deare Chriſtian) ſee that in reading and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning holy things thou follow the order and Methode ſet downe here in this place by the Apoſtle.
<note place="margin">Learne this godly Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt of al learne the knowledge of Chriſt, that thou mayſt acknowledge that all thy ſtrength and power auayleth to nothing, but to ſinning. Furthermore that by fayth thou mayſt dayly wraſtle with thy fleſhe, as hee hath taught thee in the .vii. firſt Chapters. Finally, after that thou be come to the .viii. Chapter, that is, after that thou haſt tryed the Croſſe and trybulation, after thou haſt had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this wholſome mortification, often to be repeated, then firſt of all will this neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of predeſtination, waxe ſweet vnto them, then thou ſhalt firſt feele in the .ix.x. and .xi. Chapters, how full of comfort and conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this doctrine of predeſtination is. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les thou haſt had experience and tryall of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation:
<note place="margin">Predeſtination onely comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to thoſe which are wel exerciſed in afflictions.</note> vnles thou thou haſt felt thy ſelfe to haue bene brought ſometyme euen vnto the gates of hell (as we ſee in Dauid and other Saints) thou canſt not beare or brooke thys
<pb facs="tcp:25142:24"/>doctrine and ſentence of predeſtination with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perill and daunger, without a certayne murmuring and grudging of nature agaynſt God. Therefore it is needefull and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that olde Adam ſhould firſt be mortiſied, that the ſenſe of the fleſhe ſhoulde bee beaten downe, that the ſucklings ſhould firſt grow vp in Chriſt before they drinke of this ſweete Cuppe of wine. For euen heere alſo there is in euery one a certayne infancie &amp; childhood, who hath in the meane tyme neede to be fed with Milke, vntill he be accuſtomed to eate ſtronger meates.</p>
            <p>In the twelfth chapter he dooth annex and adioyne certayne admonitions and precepts.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>12</label> For this order the Apoſtle is wont to obſerue in all his Epiſtles,
<note place="margin">The ſecond patt of this Epiſtle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation.</note> that firſt he dooth teache Chriſt and Fayth: afterwardes he dooth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort to good workes, and a continuall morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the fleſh. Wherefore he dooth teach heere good works in deede, and the true worſhip of God. And heere he maketh all Chriſtians to be Prieſtes, commaunding them to offer not moneye, eyther Oxen or Gotes (as it was the cuſtome of the Lawe) but to offer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a ſpiritual ſacrifice,
<note place="margin">A ſpirituall Prieſthood.</note> mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying the old Adam. Furthermore he dooth
<pb facs="tcp:25142:24"/>deliuer out moſt breifly vnto vs the inſtituci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; inſtruction of Chriſtian maners: as how we ſhold teach, preach, rule, &amp; gouern, namely in the church: how we ſhould ſerue our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, how we ſhould ſuffer tribulations: to be briefe, how it behoueth a Chriſtian to behaue hymſelfe towards his freendes and enemyes. And theſe are truely good workes of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man, which doo ſlow out of Fayth as from a fountaine and head ſpring. Yea which doo euen make a violent eruption. For faith (as I haue ſayd) is not ydle:
<note place="margin">Papiſts works what they are</note> But the workes of the Iuſticiaryes which are done without this liuely flame of Fayth in the hart, are but hypocrites purple ſhow, and fayned colours, wherewith they paynt themſelues outwardly, when as inwardly they are full of hatred, aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, filthines, and deceyte.</p>
            <p>In the .xiii. Chapter he teacheth vs to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to earthly and worldly Magiſtrates,
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>13</label>
               <note place="margin">Obedience to the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</note> ſeeing that al power is of God. For though the adminiſtration of the ſword, and thoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall and ciuill Lawes doo helpe nothing to the iuſtification of the hart: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bycauſe that power and authoritie is ordayned and appoynted of God, to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and preſeruation of the peace of the
<pb facs="tcp:25142:25"/>commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth, that malefactors might be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and good men defended: therefore it is to be reuerenced and honoured euen of the Saintes of God and righteous men, which otherwiſe ſtand not in neede of that au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.
<note place="margin">Loue is a ſhort ſumme of all Chriſtian due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> At the laſt he comprehendeth ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily all duetis in this one worde loue. And whereas he propoſed Chriſt as the cauſe and author of our righteouſnes, now here after a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſorte he proponeth and ſetteteth hym foorth as an example: namely that we imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and following Chriſt, ſhould ſo ſerue our neyghbour, as Chriſt hath ſerued vs.</p>
            <p>In the .xiiii.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>14</label> Chapter he teacheth that the weake in fayth not as yet expert and cunning in Chriſtian libertie,
<note place="margin">Pacience,</note> ought to be paciently to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated and borne withall through loue: alſo how we ought to vſe that libertie not to any offence, but to the inſtruction and edifying of the weake conſcience of our neyghbour. For vnles the offending of the weake be diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and warely auoyded, there will followe a diſcorde and contempt of the Goſpel: whoſe dignity and renoune it ſtandes vs greatly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to conſerue and keepe inuiolate. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were better to yeelde for a tyme to the weake in fayth, vntill they be confirmed, than
<pb facs="tcp:25142:25"/>that the Goſpell ſhould be contemned or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. And this is the cheefeſt worke of Chriſtian loue and Charitie, which very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in theſe our daies haue neede of, who abuſe their libertie by eating of fleſhe, and by other meanes, hurting weake conſciences, yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them to ſtumble as it were in the entry and doore of Chriſtianitie, before they knowe the libertie of Chriſt, and the way of ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</p>
            <p>In the .xv.
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>15</label> Chapter yet once agayne hee propoſeth Chriſt to be followed, that by his example we ſhould ſupporte and beare with the weak whoſoeuer they be, whether ſinners,
<note place="margin">VVeake bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ought to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> vnlearned, rude, and vnſkilfull, or thoſe which otherwiſe are euill mannered, or of naughty conditions. For euen theſe are not ſtreyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to be contemned, but rather to be tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſuffered vntil they be better amended. So our ſauiour Chriſt (as we ſee in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell) did beare with our ſinnes and offences: yea and at this day dooth tolerate our ſinnes, errors, and imperfections, euer reaching his ryght hand to help vs, euer ayding vs through his vnſpeakable mercy.</p>
            <p>Moreoner he prayeth for the increaſe of their fayth, peace, and ioy of conſcience, alſo
<pb facs="tcp:25142:26"/>prayſing them, and committing them to God: yet once agayne he commendeth alſo and maginfieth his office, namely howe hee maye glory in that he handleth and medleth with Gods buſines and matters, how that he doth and hath preached through the grace which he hath receyued of God, being alſo called fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen by God, &amp; not by any man. By and by after,
<note place="margin">Almes to be geuen to the poore Saintes.</note> (ſetting before them the example of the Macedonians in ſted of a little <hi>Exordium</hi> or inſinuation) he dooth very ciuilly take an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to beg and craue almes of them for the poore Saynts in Hieruſalem. To be breife, whatſoeuer this moſt Apoſtolical breſt dooth, or ſpeaketh, it is meere Charitie and loue, meere workes of fayth and of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Thus thou haſt (gentle reader) here in this Epiſtle moſt fully and abſolutely ſet out whatſoeuer appertayneth any way eyther to Chriſtian lyfe,
<note place="margin">The Epiſtle to the Romanes a ſufficient doctrine for a Chriſtian man</note> or iuſtification: what Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought cheifly to learne, namely what the lawe is, what the Goſpel is, what ſyn, grace, fayth, iuſtice or righteouſnes, Chriſt, God, good workes, charitie, loue, and hope is: brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in what thing the ſum of all Chriſtianitie dooth conſiſt: how a Chriſtian ought to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue hymſelfe towardes his neyghbour, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:25142:26"/>they be good or bad, weake or ſtrong, freindes or foes. Laſt of al how we ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues cowards our ſelues, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth ſo diligently fortifie &amp; ſtrengthen all theſe things by Scripture, and ſo confirme them by his owne example, and the example of the Prophets, that thou canſt not heere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre or wiſh any thing more, or more playne and manifeſt. For (no doubt) it was the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles mynde to comprehend in this Epiſtle ſummarily, and to handle compendiouſly the whole Goſpell, and whatſoeuer belongeth to Chriſtian learning and inſtruction, alſo to prepare a Methode and briefe introduction vnto all the writings of the olde Teſtament, namely, Moſes and the Prophets. For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath red this Epiſtle well and thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly digeſted it in his mynde, that man hath a moſt ſure and certayne Methode to all the old Teſtament.
<note place="margin">A profitable exhortation.</note> Wherefore as I admoniſhed before, ſo here now agayne I doo exhort you, that you would (as Moſes dooth in the .xi. Ch. of <hi>Deuteronomie</hi>) lay vp theſe things in your hartes, and teache them your children, to the ende that by a continual recording and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, they may be made by al meanes moſt familiar vnto you.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:27"/>
            <p>The laſt Chapter contayneth ſalutations or commendations:
<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Chap. </seg>16</label> to which he adioyneth a very good and moſt neceſſarye admonition, namely that we ſhould ſhunne and eſchew (as the plague and extreme infection and poyſon of our fayth) the doctrines and traditions of men wherewith the Goſpell and woorde of God being troden vnder foote) the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles doo ſeduce and withdrawe from Chriſt the hartes of the ſimple.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raditions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>yued.</note> For the Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſawe in the Spirit, that there ſhould ariſe and ſpring certayne Romaniſtes (for they are not worthy the name of Romanes) out of Rome, and Romanes: who by their wicked and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous, moſt diuiliſh and ſathanicall decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and their whole den of mans lawes and traditions, as by a moſt waſt floude and huge delight, would labour to drowne, extinguiſh, and deſtroy not onely this excellent Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but euen the whole bodye of Scripture: yea all the doctrine of fayth, and of the ſpirit: inſomuch that they ſhould leaue vs nothing but this Idoll our belly,
<note place="margin">Papiſtes belly gods. Philip. 3.18</note> whoſe worſhippers he dooth cal them heere, and moſt playnly in the Epiſtle to the Philippians. For (ſaith he) there be many walke, of whom I haue tolde you often, and now tell you weeping,
<pb facs="tcp:25142:27"/>they are the enemyes of the Croſſe of Chriſt whoſe God is their belly and their glory, to their ſhame, they are worldly mynded. The God of all peace bruſe and beate downe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than and hys Kingdome vnder our Foote. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Soli Deo gloria.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ <hi>Imprinted at London, nigh</hi> vnto the three Cranes in the Vintree, for Thomas Woodcock <hi>dwellyng in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the Signe of the blacke Beare.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:28"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25142:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
